In this video, I'd like to
在这个视频中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
talk about the Gaussian distribution, which
我将介绍高斯分布
is also called the normal distribution.
也称为正态分布
In case you're already intimately
如果你已经
familiar with the Gaussian distribution, it is
对高斯分布非常熟悉了
probably okay to skip this video.
那么也许你可以直接跳过这段视频
But if you're not sure or
但是 如果你不确定
if it's been a while since you've
或者你已经有段时间
worked with a Gaussian distribution or the normal
没有接触高斯分布
distribution then please do
或者正态分布了
watch this video all the way to the end.
那么 请从头到尾看完这段视频
And in the video after this,
在下一个视频中
we'll start applying the Gaussian
我们将应用高斯分布
distribution to developing an anomaly detection algorithm.
来推导一套异常检测算法
Let's say x is a
假设x是一个
real value random variable, so x is a real number.
实数随机变量 因此x是一个实数
If the probability distribution of
如果x的概率分布
x is Gaussian, it
服从高斯分布
would mean Mu and variant
其中均值为μ
sigma squared, then we'll
方差为σ平方
write this as x the
那么将它记作
random variable tilde.
随机变量x 波浪号
That's this little tilde
这个小小的波浪号
as distributed as and then
读作 服从...分布
to denote the Gaussian Distribution, sometimes
为了表示高斯分布
you're going to write script n, parentheses
有时你将使用大写字母N
Mu, sigma squared.
括号μ σ平方
So, this script's end stands for
因此这个大写字母N表示
normal, since Gaussian and normal
Normal (正态)
distribution, they mean the same
因为高斯分布就是正态分布
phase of synonymous and a
他们是同义词
Gussian distribution is parameterized
然后 高斯分布
by 2 parameters, by a
有两个参数
mean parameter which we
一个是均值
denote Mu, and a variance
我们记作μ
parameter, which we denote by sigma squared.
另一个是方差 我们记作σ平方
If we pluck the Gaussian distribution
如果我们将高斯分布
or Gaussian probability density, it
的概率密度函数绘制出来
will look like the bell shaped
它看起来将是这样一个钟形的曲线
curve, which you may have seen before.
大家之前可能就见过
And so, this bell-shaped curve
这个钟形曲线
is parameterized by those 2 parameters Mu and sigma.
有两个参数 分别是μ和σ
And the location of the
其中μ控制
center of this bell-shaped curve
这个钟形曲线
is the mean Mu, and the
的中心位置
width of this bell-shaped curve,
σ控制这个钟形曲线的宽度
so it's roughly that, is
因此 参数σ
the, this parameter
有时也称作
sigma, is also called one standard deviation.
一个标准差
And so, this specifies the
这条钟形曲线决定了
probability of x taking
x取不同数值
on different values, so x
的概率密度分布
taking on values, you know
因此 x取中心这些值
in the middle here is pretty high
的概率相当大
since the Gaussian density here
因为高斯分布的概率密度
is pretty high whereas
在这里很大
x taking on values further and
而x取远处和更远处数值
further away will be diminishing
的概率将逐渐降低
in probability. Finally, just
直至消失
for completeness, let me write
最后 为了讲述的完整性
out the formula for the Gaussian
让我写下高斯分布的数学公式
distribution so the property
x的概率分布
of x and I'll
我有时不写p(x)
sometimes write this instead of
我会用这个代替
p of x, I'm going
我会写成
to write this as p of
p 括号 x
x semicolon Mu comma sigma squared.
分号 μ 逗号 σ 平方
And so this denotes that the probability of
这个表示
x is parametrized by
x的概率分布
the two parameters Mu and sigma squared.
由两个参数控制μ和σ平方
And the formula for the
高斯分布的概率密度公式
Gaussian density is this,
是这样的
1 over 2pi, sigma e
2π开方 乘以 σ 分之 1
to the negative x minus Mu squared over 2 sigma squared.
乘以一个e的指数函数 其中指数项为 负的 x减μ的平方除以2倍的σ平方
So there's no need to memorize this
其实我们并不需要
formula, you know, this
记住这个公式
is just the formula for the
它只是左边这条钟形曲线
bell-shaped curve over here on the left.
对应的公式
There's no need to memorize it and
我们没有必要记住它
if you ever need to use this,
当我们真的需要用到它时
you can always look this up.
我们总可以查资料找到它
And so that figure on the
如果你选定
left, that is what you get
μ值
if you take a fixed
以及σ值
value of Mu and a
然后绘制p(x)曲线
fixed value of sigma and
那么你将得到
you plot p of x. So this
左边这幅图
curve here, this is really
因此这条曲线
p of x plotted as a
其实就是
function of x, you know,
给定μ值
for a fixed value of Mu
以及σ平方 也就是方差值时
and of sigma squared sigma squared, that's called the variance.
p(x)的函数图像
And sometimes it's easier to think in terms of sigma.
也许有些时候我们使用σ会更方便
So sigma is called the
而σ被称作
standard deviation and it,
标准差
so it specifies the
它确定了
width of this Gaussian probability
高斯分布概率密度函数
density whereas the square
的宽度
of sigma, so sigma squared, is
而σ平方
called the variance. Let's look
则称作方差
at some examples of what the Gaussian distribution looks like.
让我们看几个高斯分布的图像
If Mu equals zero, sigma equals 1.
如果μ取0 σ取1
Then we have a Gaussian distribution
那么我们的高斯分布
that is centered around zero, because that's Mu.
将以0为中心 因为μ等于0
And the width of this Gaussian, so
而高斯分布的宽度
that's one standard deviation is sigma over there.
将是一个标准差 也就是σ
Let's look at some examples of
让我们看几个高斯分布的图像
Gaussians. If Mu
如果μ取0
is equal to zero it equals 1.
σ取1
Then that corresponds to a
那么这将对应
Gaussian distribution that is centered
一个以0为中心
at zero since Mu is zero.
的高斯分布
And the width of this Gaussian
而高斯分布的宽度
is Gaussian thus controlled
高斯分布的宽度
by sigma by that variance parameter sigma.
由标准差σ决定
Here's another example.
来看另一个例子
Let's say Mu is equal to
如果μ取0
zero and sigma is equal to one-half.
σ取0.5
So the standard deviation is
也就是说标准差
one-half and the variance
是0.5
sigma squared would therefore be
方差σ平方
the square of 0.5 would be 0.25.
是0.5的平方 也就是0.25
And in that case the Gaussian distribution,
这时候 高斯分布
the Gaussian probability density looks
高斯分布的概率密度函数曲线
like this, is also centered at zero.
会是这样的 以0为中心
But now the width of
然而 现在它的宽度
this is much smaller because
小了许多
the smaller variance, the
因为方差变小了
width of this Gaussian density
高斯密度函数的宽度
is roughly half as wide.
大约是之前的一半
But because this is a
但是 因为这是
probability distribution, the area under
一个概率分布
the curve, that is the shaded
因此曲线下的面积
area there, that area
这些阴影区域的积分
must integrate to 1.
一定是1
This is a property of probability distributions.
这是概率分布的一个特性
And so, you know, this
因此
is a much taller Gaussian density because
这个高斯密度曲线更高
it's half as wide, with
因为它只有一半宽
half the standard deviation, but it's twice as tall.
只有一半的标准差 但是它有两倍高
Another example, if sigma is
再看一个例子
equal to 2, then you
如果σ等于2
get a much fatter, or much wider Gaussian density.
那么你将得到一个更胖更宽的高斯密度曲线
And so here, the sigma
在这里
parameter controls that this
σ参数决定了
Gaussian density has a wider width.
曲线会更宽
And once again, the area under
同样的
the curve, that is this shaded
曲线下方的面积 这快阴影区域
area, you know, it always integrates to 1.
的积分一定是1
That's a property of probability
这是概率分布的一个特性
distributions, and because it's
因为它更宽
wider, it's also half as
因此它只有一半高
tall, in order to just integrate to the same thing.
这样积分才能保持不变
And finally, one last example would be,
最后一个例子
if we now changed the Mu
如果我们也改变参数μ
parameters as well, then instead
那么曲线
of being centered at zero, we
将不再以0为中心
now we have a Gaussian distribution
现在我们的高斯分布
that is centered at three, because
以3为中心
this shifts over the entire Gaussian distribution.
因为整个高斯分布被平移了
Next, lets take about the parameter estimation problem.
接下来 让我们来看参数估计问题
So what is the parameter estimation problem?
那么 什么是参数估计问题？
Let's say we have a data set
假设我们有一个数据集
of m examples, so x1
其中有m个样本
through x(m), and let's say
从x(1)到x(m)
each of these examples is a real number.
假设他们都是实数
Here in the figure, I've plotted an
在这幅图里
example of a data set,
我画出了整个数据集
so the horizontal axis is the
图中的横轴
x axis and, you know, I
是x轴
have a range of examples of x and I've just plotted them
我的样本x取值分布广泛
on this figure here.
我就将它们画在这里
And the parameter estimation problem is, let's
而参数估计问题就是
say I suspect that these examples
假设我猜测这些样本
came from a Gaussian distribution so
来自一个高斯分布的总体
let's say I suspect that each of my example x(i) was distributed.
假设我猜测每一个样本xi服从某个分布
That's what this tilde thing means.
这里的波浪号表示 服从...分布
Thus, I suspect that each of
因此 我猜测
these examples was distributed according
这里的每个样本
to a normal distribution or
服从正态分布
Gaussian distribution with some
或者高斯分布
parameter Mu and some parameter sigma squared.
它有两个参数 μ和σ平方
But I don't know what the values of these parameters are.
然而 我不知道这些参数的值是多少
The problem with parameter estimation is,
参数估计问题就是
given my data set I want
给定数据集
to figure out, I want to
我希望能找到
estimate, what are the
能够估算出
values of Mu and sigma squared.
μ和σ平方的值
So, if you're given a
因此 如果你有
data set like this, you know,
这样一个数据
it looks like maybe, if I
它看起来好像
estimate what Gaussian distribution the
如果我试图找到
data came from, maybe that
它来自哪个高斯分布
might be roughly the Gaussian distribution
也许这个就是
it came from, with Mu
它对应的高斯分布
being the center of the distribution and
其中μ对应分布函数的中心
sigma the standard deviation controlling the width of this Gaussian distribution.
而标准差σ控制高斯分布的宽度
It seems like a reasonable
这条曲线似乎
fit to the data, because, you know, it
很好的拟合了数据
looks the data has
因为看起来
a very high probability of being
这个数据集
in the central region, low probability of
在中心区域的概率比较大
being further out, low probability of being further out, and so on.
而在外围 在边缘的概率越来越小
And so, maybe this is
因此 也许这是
a reasonable estimate of
对μ和σ平方
Mu and of sigma squared,
的一个不错的估计
that is, if it corresponds to
也就是说
a Gaussian distribution, that then looks like this.
我们的数据对应这样一个高斯分布
So, what I'm going to
那么 接下来
do is write out the
我将写下
formulas, the standard formulas
对μ和σ平方
for estimating the parameters from
进行参数估计的
Mu and sigma squared.
标准公式
The way we are going to
我们估计μ的方法是
estimate Mu is going to
对我的
be just the average
所有样本
of my example.
求平均值
So Mu is the mean parameter,
μ就是平均值参数
so I'm going to take my
因此 我将
training set, take my m
使用我的训练集
examples and average them.
使用我的m个样本 对它们取平均
And that just gives me the center of this distribution.
这样我就得到了高斯分布的中心位置
How about sigma squared?
那么如何估计σ平方呢？
Well the variance, I'll just
σ平方表示方差
write out the standard formula again,
我们也来写下方差的标准计算公式
I'm going to estimate as sum
我先将所有的样本
of 1 through m of x(i),
从x(1)到x(m)
minus Mu squared,
减去平均值μ
and so this Mu here is
平方再求和
actually the Mu that I compute
实际上μ是用
over here using this formula,
之前的这个公式计算出来的
and what the variance is, or
而方差的含义
one interpretation of the variance,
至少一种方差的定义
is that, if you look at the
是将这一项
this term, that's the square
所有样本
difference between the value
的差值平方和
I've got in my example minus
我已经将样本减去了平均值
the mean, minus the center, minus the mean of distribution.
减去了中心位置 分布的平均值
And so, you know, the
因此 你看
variance, I'm gonna estimate
我会将方差估计为
as just the average of
样本减去平均值
the square differences, between my examples, minus the mean.
差值取平方 再求平均
And as a side comment,
这里顺便提一下
only for those of you that are experts
你们有些人
in statistics, if you're
可能精通统计学
an expert in statistics and if
如果你是统计方面的专家
you've heard of maximum likelihood estimation,
听说过极大似然估计
then these estimates are actually the
那么这里的估计
maximum likelihood estimates of the parameters
实际就是对μ和σ平方
of Mu and sigma squared.
的极大似然估计
But if you haven't heard of that before, don't worry about it.
不过如果你没听说过这些 没关系
All you need to know is that
你只需要知道
these are the two standard formulas
这里有两个标准公式
for how you try to
给定数据集 你可以利用它们
figure out what our Mu and sigma squared given the dataset.
估算出μ和σ平方的值
Finally one last side comment.
最后 再提一句
Again only for those of
同样是针对那些
you that has maybe taken a statistics class before.
学习过统计课程的人
But if you have taken a statistics
如果你以前上过统计课程
class before, some of you
你们可能会见过
may have seen the formula here
这么一个公式
where, you know, this is m minus
在这里不是m
1, instead of m. So
而是m减1
this first term becomes 1
第一项写成
over m minus 1, instead
m减1分之1
of 1 over m. In machine
而不是m分之1
learning, people tend to use this 1 over m formula.
在机器学习领域 大家喜欢用m分之1
But in practice, whether it
然而在实际使用中
is 1 over m or 1
到底是选择使用
over m minus one, makes essentially
m分之1还是m减1分之1
no difference, assuming, you know, m is
其实区别很小
reasonably large, it's a large training set size.
只要你有一个还算大的训练集
So, just in case you've seen
因此 如果你见过m减1分之1
this other version before, in either
这个版本的公式
version it works just equally
它同样可以很好的估计出参数
well, but in machine
只是在机器学习领域
learning most people tend to
大部分人更习惯使用
use 1 over m in this formula.
m分之1这个版本的公式
And the two versions have slightly
这两个版本的公式
different theoretical properties, slightly different
在理论特性和数学特性上稍有不同
mathematical properties, but in
但是在实际使用中
practice it really makes very little difference, if any.
他们的区别甚小 几乎可以忽略不计
So, hopefully, you now have
现在 我想
a good sense of what the
你大概已经对高斯分布的样子
Gaussian distribution looks like,
有些感觉了
as well as how to estimate
你也知道
the parameters, mu and sigma
如何估计高斯分布中的
squared, of the Gaussian distribution, and
参数μ和σ平方
if you're given a training set,
只要你有一个训练集
that is if you're given a
如果你猜测它
set of data that you suspect
来自一个高斯分布
comes from a Gaussian
你就可以估计出它的参数值
distribution with unknown parameters using sigma squared.
μ和σ平方
In the next video, we'll start
在下一个视频中
to take this and apply it
我们将利用这些知识
to develop the anomaly detection algorithm.
推导出异常检测算法